Office of the Dean of Student Affairs Records UA038
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Office of the Dean of Student Affairs Records
1972 -- 1989
1966 -- 2021
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Dean of Student Affairs
Dean of Student Services
UA038
6.75 Linear Feet 5 boxes
825 Megabytes
1,398 Digital Object(s)
This collection contains annual reports generated by the Office of the Dean of Student Affairs, submitted to the Dean of Faculty of Arts and Sciences, subject files generated by the Dean of Students between 1967 and 1999, and campus announcements sent out via email.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series: Annual reports; Subject files; Unprocessed accessions; and Campus announcements.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains annual reports generated by the Office of the Dean of Student Affairs, submitted to the Dean of Faculty of Arts and Sciences, subject files generated by the Dean of Students between 1967 and 1999, and campus announcements sent out via email. Offices that submitted reports include: The Asian American Center; the Hispanic American Center; The Department of Housing and Campus Life; The African American Center; the Counseling Center; the Health Service; the Office of Student Activities; the Department of Arts, Sciences, and Technology; the Associate Dean of Students; and the Office of Women's Programs. Subject files include information on Academic awards, the African American Center, various commencement ceremonies (1976-1994), the Committee on Academic Standing, the Counseling Center, fraternities, the Faculty and Staff Financial Aid Committee (1981-1982), housing, the International Center, parent weekends, and student activities.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Biographical / Historical
The Office of the Dean of Students is responsible for overseeing all non-academic student activities on Tufts campus. Historically, this has included overseeing financial aid funds, interactions between different student groups on campus, disciplinary committees, counseling services, minority enrollment, and other subjects. It is made up of the Dean of Student Affairs, and several associate deans and specialists.
The position was established in 1969, and headed by Alvin R. Schmidt until he ceded the position in 1974. It combined the two previous roles of Dean of Men and the recently created Dean of Women. The latter had been established in 1967, taking on some of the responsibilities which the Dean of Jackson College previously held. Before 1967, Dean of Men and Student Personnel was the only position which dealt directly with student involvement.
By 2007, the name "Office of the Dean of Students" was changed to "Office of the Dean of Student Affairs," with the position "Dean of Students" receiving the same name change to reflect the changing responsibilities of the role. When the position had been established, the responsibilities of the role had required more direct oversight of student activities, as the team was much smaller. Though this still remained a part of the job and a fundamental part of the office, as the team expanded, the position started to require more supervisory capabilities and less interaction directly with students.
By 2021, the Office of the Dean of Student Affairs had been reorganized into the Division of Student Affairs, led by the Dean of Student Affairs and Chief Student Affairs Officer. The Division includes the Office of the Dean of Student Affairs, Office of Residential Life and Learning, Health and Wellness, SMFA Student Affairs, Student Affairs Communications, Career Services, and Office of Campus Life.
General
Known as the Office of the Dean of Students prior to 2007.
Student Affairs and Services; Student life; Student activities
- Dean of Students, annual reports, 1970 -- 1998; UA038.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the annual reports generated by the Office of the Dean of Students, submitted to the Dean of Faculty of Arts and Sciences. These reports included the annual reports submitted to the Office of the Dean of Students. The offices which submitted reports include; The Asian American Center, the Hispanic American Center, The Department of Housing and Campus Life, The African American Center, the Counselling Cemter, the Health Service, the Office of Student Activities, the Department of Arts, Sciences, and Technology, the Associate Dean of Students, the Office of Women's Programs.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Annual reports, 1970 -- 1971; UA038.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1971 -- 1972; UA038.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1972 -- 1973; UA038.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1973 -- 1974; UA038.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1974 -- 1975; UA038.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1978 -- 1989; UA038.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1987 -- 1988; UA038.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1988 -- 1989; UA038.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1988 -- 1989; UA038.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1989; UA038.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1989; UA038.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1989; UA038.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1990; UA038.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1990; UA038.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1990 -- 1991; UA038.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1990 -- 1991; UA038.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1991 -- 1992; UA038.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1991 -- 1992; UA038.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1991 -- 1992; UA038.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1992 -- 1993; UA038.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1993; UA038.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1994; UA038.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1994 -- 1995; UA038.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1995 -- 1996; UA038.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1996; UA038.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1997; UA038.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Annual records, 1997 -- 1998; UA038.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
- Dean of students, subject files, 1967 -- 1999; UA038.002; 1.95 Linear Feet
  This series contains subject files pertaining to the Dean of Students. These files include information on; Academic awards, the African American Center, various commencement ceremonies (1976-94), the Committee on Academic Standing, the Counseling Center, fraternities, the Faculty and Staff Financial Aid Committee (1981-82), housing, the International Center, parent weekends, and student activities.
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Academic awards, 1967 -- 1981; UA038.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Academic awards, 1982; UA038.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Academic awards, 1983; UA038.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - African American center, 1973 -- 1978; UA038.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - African American center, 1983 -- 1986; UA038.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - African American center, 1987; UA038.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - African American center, 1987; UA038.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - African American center, 1988 -- 1990; UA038.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - African American center, 1991 -- 1994; UA038.002.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - African American center, previous directors, 1999; UA038.002.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Black caucus, 1993; UA038.002.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Chalking policy, 1993; UA038.002.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Chemical dependency collaborative, 1989; UA038.002.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Chemical dependency collaborative, 1991; UA038.002.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - Cleary legislation, 1992; UA038.002.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - Commencement, 1976 -- 1980; UA038.002.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Commencement, 1982 -- 1984; UA038.002.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - Commencement, 1994; UA038.002.002.00018 (Box 2)
  - Committee on academic standing, 1975 -- 1981; UA038.002.002.00019 (Box 2)
  - Committee on academic standing, 1981 -- 1982; UA038.002.002.00020 (Box 2)
  - Committee on academic standing, 1982 -- 1983; UA038.002.002.00021 (Box 2)
  - Counseling center, 1979 -- 1997; UA038.002.002.00022 (Box 2)
  - Counseling center, 1979 -- 1997; UA038.002.002.00023 (Box 2)
  - Date rape material, 1991; UA038.002.002.00024 (Box 2)
  - Demonstrations, disturbances: policy, 1985; UA038.002.002.00025 (Box 2)
  - Diversity, 1991; UA038.002.002.00026 (Box 2)
  - Diversity, 1997; UA038.002.002.00027 (Box 2)
  - Diversity, 1997; UA038.002.002.00028 (Box 2)
  - Diversity, sexual orientation, 1992; UA038.002.002.00029 (Box 2)
  - Divestment, 1986; UA038.002.002.00030 (Box 2)
  - Faculty and staff: financial aid committee, 1981 -- 1982; UA038.002.002.00031 (Box 2)
  - Faculty and staff: financial aid committee, 1981 -- 1982; UA038.002.002.00032 (Box 2)
  - Free speech, 1992 -- 1996; UA038.002.002.00033 (Box 2)
  - Free speech policy, 1990; UA038.002.002.00034 (Box 2)
  - Fraternities, 1986 -- 1988; UA038.002.002.00035 (Box 2)
  - Fraternities,ad-hoc committee on fraternities and sororities, 1986 -- 1992; UA038.002.002.00036 (Box 2)
  - Fraternities, discipline, 1993; UA038.002.002.00037 (Box 2)
  - Fraternities, hazing, 1996; UA038.002.002.00038 (Box 2)
  - Fraternities, recognition, UA038.002.002.00039 (Box 2)
  - Graduate school, 1990 -- 1995; UA038.002.002.00040 (Box 2)
  - Hazing law, 1989; UA038.002.002.00041 (Box 2)
  - Health services: committee on organization of health services, 1979; UA038.002.002.00042 (Box 2)
  - Homeless, Joel, 1992; UA038.002.002.00043 (Box 2)
  - Housing, 1989 -- 1992; UA038.002.002.00044 (Box 2)
  - Housing, 1995 -- 1998; UA038.002.002.00045 (Box 2)
  - Housing, hillside house, 1993; UA038.002.002.00046 (Box 2)
  - Housing, undergraduate, 1981; UA038.002.002.00047 (Box 2)
  - International center, 1988 -- 1992; UA038.002.002.00048 (Box 2)
  - Jackson Jills, 1994 -- 1995; UA038.002.002.00049 (Box 2)
  - Liability and legal issues, 1985 -- 1990; UA038.002.002.00050 (Box 2)
  - Liability and legal issues, privacy, 1975 -- 1983; UA038.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Light on the Hill, 1998 -- 1999; UA038.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Nondiscrimination, 1985; UA038.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Parent's weekend, 1977 -- 1983; UA038.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - PDQ (position description questionnaire), 1994; UA038.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Photos, 1988; UA038.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - RA dorm selection, 1984 -- 1985; UA038.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Racial issues, 1987 -- 1988; UA038.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Search: director of auxilary services, 1984; UA038.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Search: sexuality and health, 1983 -- 1984; UA038.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Search: university chaplain, 1977 -- 1981; UA038.002.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Search: university chaplain, 1977 -- 1981; UA038.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Social policy, 1986 -- 1987; UA038.002.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Student activities, 1986; UA038.002.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - Student faculty issues, 1983; UA038.002.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Student treatment, 1979 -- 1992; UA038.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Subcommittee on counseling service, 1980; UA038.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Trustees:board of overseers of student life, 1989 -- 1994; UA038.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
- Additional accessions, 1966 -- 1999; UA038.003
  - Dean of students, disciplinary handbooks info. for students with disabilities and academic advising pamphlets, parents' weekend info., 1966 -- 1999; UA038-001 (Box 1)
- Campus announcements, 2019 -- 2021; UA038.000101; 825 Megabytes; 1398 Digital Object(s)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  This material was downloaded directly from Emma, an email marketing system used by the Office of the Dean of Students. The emails were downloaded as PDFs by the Records and Accessioning Archivist, Jane Kelly, in April 2021, accession UA-2021-043.
  This series contains emails sent to students and families by a variety of campus offices. These offices include the Office of the Dean of Students, the Office for Campus Life, the identity centers, and the Career Center. Topics of these emails include academic and career advising, campus events, COVID-19 pandemic updates, and general student life announcements.
  - Campus announcements, 2019 -- 2021; UA038.000102; 825 Megabytes; 1398 Digital Object(s)